Fletcher School Records UA015
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Fletcher program theses, 1981 -- 2015; UA015.012; 286 Digital Object(s); 1 Volumes
  - When Do We Get to Peace? Patterns of Gender-Based Violence in Post-Conflict Liberia, 2007; UA015.012.075.00014; Bruno, Emily K.; Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree of Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: The research sought to understand some of the ranges of experiences of women and girls in post-conflict societies by examining the types, frequency, and nature of gender violence that women and girls experience in post-conflict Liberia. Given the nature and scale of sexual violence during the fourteen year civil conflict, what are the patterns of gender violence in post-conflict Liberia? Has sexual violence continued, and, if so, who is affected and how? Does the potential continuation of sexual violence reflect an attempt by men to reassert their authority and control over women and in society? Has there been an increase in domestic violence since the end of the war, and if so, is this in any way correlated with men pushing back on women and the public spaces and roles they filled in political, economic, and social life during the war? In light of post-conflict violence and poverty, what opportunities exist for women to mobilize in prevention and response to gender violence, and what barriers to justice exist for women and girls? Can we document any effective models for resistance to violence from the Liberian context? Given the frameworks that we have for understanding gender-based violence in conflict and post-conflict settings, this research seeks to understand what the reported violence in Liberia says about the aftermath of war for Liberian women and society in general. While this research was primarily exploratory in nature, I undertook it with a hypothesis that there has been an increase in domestic violence since the war ended, as has been documented in other post-conflict countries, and that women and communities may not have the access to services or criminal justice systems that they need in order to address the post-conflict violence. Additionally, because many Liberian women were extremely politically active in spearheading the Liberian peace movement and negotiations, I hypothesized that there would be tension around women's post-conflict social, economic, and political roles, which may cause violence between men and women at the inter-personal level.
  - The Political Potential of Israel-GCC Business Relations, 2009; UA015.012.075.00015; Shaham, Dahlia; Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree of Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: The economic discussion of the Arab-Israeli conflict and peace process has been governed over the years by two contradicting paradigms: the Arab Boycott and the vision of the New Middle East. Over the course of the past two decades both paradigms have been eroded. The Arab Boycott, which was once a comprehensive system of political and legal dams that hindered the flow of goods, services and information between Israel and the Arab world has been largely reduced to rubble by trade agreements and economic globalization. However, the alternative vision of a New Middle East in which peace agreements usher in unlimited economic cooperation and mounting peace dividends, has not materialized either. The first chapter of this paper explains the evolution of these paradigms. The paper then explores the reality of Israeli-Arab business relations and under the current conditions of continued Israeli-Palestinian conflict. It focuses on the special case of the GCC states, which are the richest and most globalized economies in the region. The second chapter outlines the history of Israeli-GCC relations; the third chapter exposes the reality of the officially non-existent Israel-GCC business relations - the sectors in which they are created and the bypass mechanisms used to facilitate them. Finally, the fourth chapter discusses the ways in which these business relations may affect the political reality of Arab-Israeli relations.
    MALD thesis; International Business Relations; International Negotiation and Conflict Resolution; International Political Economy; International Trade and Commercial Policies
  - Profits, Planes and Policy: An Analysis of the Midway Airport Privatization and its Implications for Future Airport Privatizations in the United States, 2009; UA015.012.075.00016; Cartmell, Sarah; Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree of Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: Midway International Airport in Chicago is poised to become the first large hub U.S. airport to be privatized through a 99-year lease and concession to the private sector. This precedent-setting airport privatization presents America's air transportation and infrastructure investment communities with a rich opportunity for discerning the immediate impact and broader implications of a domestic airport privatization. The Midway Airport privatization crests a confluence of forces that have made airport privatization an attractive and viable option for meeting the current and future needs of airports, and those of their public owners. America's aviation infrastructure requires far-reaching and expensive upgrades at a time when traditional airport financing modes are falling short. Further compounding this development are the mounting pressures on public budgets that serve to relegate infrastructure spending to a second-tier priority. At the same time, global infrastructure investors have amassed the money and trained their sights on transportation assets that provide steady cash flows. Both demand and supply line up to create an investment climate conducive to airport privatization. However, the theoretical arguments supporting and opposing airport privatization reveal a host of unresolved issues that serve to render airport privatization no panacea to the challenges facing the system. Instead, the theory and previous airport privatization experiences -- both domestic and international -- highlight the difficulty of undertaking a privatization and the inherent trade-offs involved. Most importantly, limited competition among airports makes efficiency gains under private ownership a questionable outcome. Against this backdrop, the Midway Airport privatization was structured and pursued to maximize upfront financial gain to the City of Chicago. This approach is problematic for several reasons: It reduced future revenue streams from the airport to the city; forced the city to incur ongoing financial obligations at Midway Airport that whittle down the amount netted from the transaction; and increased the risk of an overvaluation that will make it difficult for MIDCo to earn reasonable returns, thus ensuring precipitous price increases for airport users. While predicting the future financial and operational performance of a privatized Midway is difficult, the unresolved issues outlined above should give pause to other public airport owners considering airport privatization. The Midway International Airport privatization demonstrates that future airport privatizations in the United States should evolve beyond the narrow motive of immediate revenue generation to assume a structure that secures the diversion of long-term sustainable cash flows from the privatized airport and that provides for more competition and efficiency gains. Addendum: On April 20, 2009, the City of Chicago announced that the 99-year lease and concession of Midway Airport to MIDCo had collapsed. According to the city, MIDCo was unable to secure the financing necessary to make its $2.521 billion upfront payment to the city. Current city Chief Financial Officer Gene Saffold said the deal's collapse was attributable to the global economic crisis and liquidity crunch, which had severely impacted the availability of financing. Saffold also stated the city's intention to re-bid Midway Airport when market conditions improve.
    MALD thesis; International Business and Economic Law; International Business Relations; International Political Economy
  - Tourism and Economic Development in Tanzania, 2009; UA015.012.075.00017; Sitts, Sarah; Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree of Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: Tanzania is richly endowed in natural beauty, but most of its inhabitants are poor. Tourism presents an opportunity to capitalize on the world class concentrations of wildlife in the Northern Safari Circuit and the beautiful beaches of Zanzibar by generating income while sustaining the natural resources. This paper examines the ways in which the tourism industry contributes to economic development among Tanzanians. A value chain mapping approach to the two regions' tourism industries illustrates how much of the value is controlled by 'primary companies', hotels and, in the Northern Circuit, safari companies. Nine channels are identified through which tourism provides economic benefits to the poor, along with the channels' current limitations and the author's recommendations for enhancing their 'pro poor' outcomes. To consider the overall net benefits of tourism, the benefits are balanced by the negative social, environmental and economic impacts tourism has on Tanzanians. Key recommendations for enhancing the industry's overall economic development contributions are addressed to key players Ð primary businesses, the Tanzanian and Zanzibari governments, and international agencies Ð while recognizing the likely barriers to the policies' implementation.
    MALD thesis; International Political Economy
  - Unraveling the Paradox: The Resilience of Women's Rights Activism in Iran within the Context of a Changing Political Environment, 2009; UA015.012.075.00018; Haeri, Medina; Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree of Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: This thesis proposes to unravel the paradox of women's rights activism in Iran through a critical examination of women's rights activities starting in the time of the Shah and continuing into the first twenty years of the Islamic Revolution. It will consider the reasons why women were not able to retain the legal rights they achieved during the Shah's regime, once the Islamic Republic emerged after the revolution. In contrast, despite the imposition of restrictive Islamic laws following the revolution, women's rights activism has continued to flourish and today, women have emerged as a deliberate and indigenous constituency in their own right. Unraveling the paradox means studying the factors and events that have shaped women's activism in Iran and realizing that despite changing political contexts and changing strategic tactics, the basic demands and desires of women in Iran have remained basically the same for the past forty years.
    MALD thesis; Human Security; Southwest Asia and Islamic Civilization
  - The WTO Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights and the Doha Declaration on TRIPS and Public Health: Will They Solve the Pharmaceutical Question?, 2009; UA015.012.075.00019; Lima, Rafael Cavazzoni; Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree of Master of Laws in International Law at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: The Agreement in Trade-Related Intellectual Property Rights (the TRIPs Agreement) transformed the standing of intellectual property in international law by incorporating into the legal framework of the World Trade Organization (WTO) an improved system of standards for the protection of a full range of intellectual property (IP) rights, including copyrights, patents, trademarks, industrial designs, trade secrets and geographical indications. This paper intends to offer the reader an analysis of the impact of the TRIPs agreement on the access to medicines in developing countries. More specifically, this dissertation aims to elucidate and explain the existing legal regime regulating the grant of compulsory licenses by developing countries for the implementation of domestic programs in the area of public health after the Doha Declaration. This legal examination will be followed by an interesting policy-oriented analysis. In this part of the paper, the cases of Rwanda, Brazil and Thailand will be properly addressed. The intention is to provide an opinion about the system that is currently in place and to analyze whether the Doha Declaration and sequential actions were able to put an end to what was referred to as "The Pharmaceutical Question." Finally, the paper will offer a few ideas for making this system work better.
    LLM thesis; Public Health; International law; Biotechnology; Health policy; Intellectual Property
  - Achieving universal health coverage in Mexico: The case of Seguro Popular, 2010; UA015.012.077.00001; Flores, Barbara E. Bravo; Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree of Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: The creation of Seguro Popular in 2003 has represented an extraordinary achievement for health policy in Mexico: it had made access to health care a reality for millions of low income Mexican families. Despite the groundbreaking reforms enacted during the previous government, several issues remained unresolved by the time Calderón took office in December of 2006. The successful adjustments made to the program as it was aggressively expanded during the previous three years had made the goal of universal access to health possible.
    MALD thesis; Health policy; Medical care
  - Theorizing the Economics of E-Waste Trade: Issues, Analysis and Strategies, 2010; UA015.012.077.00002; Relhan, Gaurav; Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree of Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: To many a perceptive mind, the trade in E-Waste products should ideally be termed 'illegal' in view of the social hazards and moral shortcomings involved in exporting used, unreliable ICT equipment to developing countries, and consequently exposing marginalized workers to health hazards. But in the face of lax regulations imposed by E-Waste trading nations and only ad-hoc attempts made to curtail E-Waste trade, such is the magnitude of this unregulated waste flow, that it may actually be characterized in quantitative terms as 'free' trade, despite multilateral treaties which regulate trade in 'hazardous' products. This thesis investigates through trade economics the assumption that the economic gains harvested by e-waste exchanging partners are welfare-enhancing enough that it becomes economically viable to condone the environmental and social costs borne by E-Waste receiving nations. In other words, this thesis explores whether E-Waste trade does in fact bring overall mutual economic gains to participating economies, thereby providing a logic behind lax regulation by governments.
    MALD thesis; International Trade and Commerce Policies; Technology transfer; Electronic waste
  - Evaluating the Effectiveness of the Capstone Doctrine in Addressing UN Peacekeeping Challenges, 2010; UA015.012.077.00003; Christensen, Colin W.; Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree of Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: The United Nations originally developed the concept of peacekeeping and has far more experience with the practice than any other international or multi-lateral body. While it possesses substantial expertise in carrying out peacekeeping missions, it now faces a range of serious challenges to its capacity to continue doing so effectively. These challenges are not new, however, and in its long history with peacekeeping the UN has progressively evolved in its approach to the practice. In January, 2008, the Department of Peacekeeping Operations (DPKO) approved the Capstone Doctrine (Capstone) as a way of helping to bring the lessons-learned of past peacekeeping operations under one conceptual roof (Capstone is officially titled the United Nations Peacekeeping Operations, Principles and Guidelines). In this paper I will examine the challenges faced by contemporary peacekeeping and look at how Capstone attempts to respond to these challenges. I conclude that Capstone addresses most, but not all of these challenges. In doing so, it presents a fundamentally conservative vision of peacekeeping, although it also leaves conceptual room open for some expansive interpretations of particular peacekeeping activities. I find that Capstone's direct impact is fairly limited to educational materials and as a potential reference tool for peacekeeping policymakers.
    MALD thesis; Peace; International Negotiation and Conflict Resolution
  - The Responsibility to Protect: Issues of Legal Formulation and Practical Application, 2010; UA015.012.077.00004; Kantareva, Silva D.; Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree of Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract:he codification of the doctrine of the 'responsibility to protect' at the World Summit meeting in 2005 is emblematic of the increasing importance attributed to human security in world affairs today. An indication of the growing recognition that state sovereignty 'finds limits in the protection of human security,' the responsibility to protect, also known as R2P, posits an alternative interpretation of sovereignty-one that is no longer just a right in Westphalian terms, but one that also creates obligations for States with respect to the security of their subjects. As a doctrine, R2P encompasses a number of normative tenets with varying degrees of legal acceptance, the most controversial of which seeks to permit coercive intervention, under certain conditions. Given the wide and long-standing acceptance for the preventive and peace-building aspects of the doctrine, the real debate surrounding R2P is a rehash of the long-standing discussion on 'just war' and humanitarian intervention. While far from crystallizing into anything resembling binding law, R2P can arguably impact the justificatory discourse in international law and raise the political costs of action or inaction in the face of gross human rights violations. By creating a sense of moral obligation among States, through a repeated process of interaction, interpretation and internalization, R2P has the potential to spur a 'coincidence of interest.' With this paper, I will examine whether it is justified to speak of an emerging norm in the case of R2P; whether state practice in the area demonstrates any conformity to this principle; and whether there is any evidence in international discourse of a broad consensus (opinio juris) with respect to its legality. In order to judge the potential for such an outcome to develop, a useful starting point would be to track the frequency and nature of recourse to this concept in international discourse, and more specifically, within the General Assembly and the United Nations Security Council, which, insofar as coercive action is concerned, has been officially charged with the responsibility to protect. Five years into its official 'endorsement,' the responsibility to protect has been barely made operational and has done very little by way of affecting discourse among Member States. The Security Council is yet to translate R2P in a meaningful way even though it has had ample opportunities to invoke R2P, in the cases of Sri Lanka, Zimbabwe, Somalia or Myanmar. It certainly failed to operationalize it in the cases of Darfur and the DRC. What is more, there seems to be little agreement among the membership as to the scope and operational parameters of R2P, as becomes obvious from recent debates in the General Assembly. The conduct and statements of States do not give weight to the idea that humanitarian intervention, albeit under a different nomenclature, is now legal or justified by this nascent doctrine.
    MALD thesis; Human Security; Human rights; International law
  - Judicial Reform in Afghanistan: Towards a Holistic Understanding of Legitimacy in Post-Conflict Societies, 2010; UA015.012.077.00005; Christensen, Maren I.; Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree of Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: This investigation seeks to elucidate the connections among three aspects of rule of law through an examination of judicial reform in post-Taliban Afghanistan. I hypothesize that building judicial independence, engagement with customary law, and anti-corruption efforts, usually approached separately, are interdependent through their impacts on legitimacy. Failings in post-2001 Afghanistan, particularly the insistence on building rule of law from the top-down, have resulted in a formal judiciary that is neither independent, nor accountable, nor culturally viable. Taking note of the way in which these failings are being harnessed by the insurgency to further divide the nation as a whole and prevent the state from building legitimacy, the theoretical hypothesis is supported: effectiveness and appeal to tradition are necessary conditions for building legitimacy. These conditions are satisfied, respectively, through (1) successful anti-corruption and independent, sustainable institution building, and (2) consultation and genuine engagement with all sources of traditional authority. Having come to an understanding of the importance of bottom-up and top-down rule of law, I recommend that while we sustain our efforts in anti-corruption and institution building in the formal sector, we also need direct engagement that is community-specific: bringing together traditional leaders, local state justice officials, and progressive stakeholders such as women's rights advocates to come to a better understanding of each other's intentions, priorities, practices and values. This kind of dialogue would build non-coercive consensus on an arrangement that covers all bases in the administration of justice between the courts and informal jirgas or shuras. Once a number of these groups have been successful, there will be stronger impetus to replicate this dialogue at the national level, bridging top-down institution building and legal development with bottom-up social transformation. Such a holistic approach would garner state legitimacy in a way that is simultaneously modern, effective, and genuinely Afghan.
    MALD thesis; Rule of law; Nation-building; Comparative and Developmental Political Analysis; Postwar reconstruction